# 大家好 你看 我家的茶園
Hi everyone! Look! In my tea plantation,
# 現在開了好多花呀
there are a lot of flowers now.
# 這個還小的時候 我們經常摘這個花
These flowers, as kids, we always picked these flowers.
# 摘來這樣
And then we,
# 這樣吸一下
suck it.
# 這裡面的 花 那個甚麼
Inside, there is, nec..how is it called?
# 蜜 有 有一點點蜜的
Nectar, there's a little bit nectar.
# 很甜的
It's really sweet.
# 你看 這種
Look! It's kind of...
# 你看 這個
Look! This is...
# 這一點點
It's just a tiny little bit.
# 這一點點 這裡面的蜜很甜的
It's just a bit. The nectar inside is really sweet,
# 跟蜜糖一樣
just like honey.
# 好甜哦
Sweet!
# 找一個
Let me get a,
# 漂亮一點的來
prettier one.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one is,
# 含花待放的 (註︰他的錯用/誤用成語有時真的令人很頭痛)
is about to blossom.
# 它這個
Look at this,
# 看那 就這 這一點點蜜
here. It's just, just a tiny little bit of nectar.
# 你看 就那麼一點點
Look! It's just a little bit.
# 有點甜
It's a bit sweet.
# 嗯 還可以喲
Um! Not too bad.
# 看下還有沒有
Let's see if there are any more.
# 這幾個花樹哇 我每年都可以搞個兩三斤茶葉
From this couple of tea trees, I have a kilo or a kilo and a half of tea leaves every year.
# 這個茶很好喝的哦
The tea tastes really nice.
# 好香的
It smells really good.
# 嗯 好甜
Um! Sweet!
# 這些荼枯萎之後哇 它就長那個茶果
When the flowers wither, they will become fruits,
# 它們都 這一個
They all…here's one,
# 一粒粒的小荼果
several tiny fruits.
# 長出來之後 這個也可以榨油的
When they grow up, they can also be pressed for oil,
# 這個也很好吃的哦
and they taste really good too.
# 但是這個量少
But the yield is low.
# 畢竟沒種多少
We're not growing a lot of them after all.
# 種了有幾十 十幾棵吧
I think we have dozens, a dozen of them,
# 20棵都不知有沒有
perhaps not even twenty.
# 今年
This year,
# 明天春天我們又可以摘這個茶葉
in the spring next year, we can pick the tea leaves again.
# 這個還有 遇有個小小的尖尖
This one has a, has a slightly pointed tip.
# 長出來之後就可以
After growing up, we can,
# 把它摘下來炒 (註︰炒葉不直用"fry"因為不加油)
pick them and then dry them,
# 炒乾
dry them in a pan.
# 炒乾那個茶葉
Dry the tea leaves.
# 很香的哦
It smells really good.
# 這個整個村裡面都沒有多少棵啦 這種茶種
There, there are not so many this kind of trees in our village.
# 這個茶樹我們也不知道叫 不知道叫甚麼茶
Nobody knows how this kind of tea, how it is called.
# 就是以前 很早很早以前 就是
It's like, in the past, I mean long long ago,
# 應該是爺爺的爺爺帶過來的
perhaps they were taken here by the grandpa of my grandpa.
# 種在這裡
And then they planted it here,
# 插在這裡
put it here.
# 種下去之後幾乎都不冋澆水 不用管的
Once planted, these trees don't really need to be watered. They don't need to be looked after.
# 修都不用修
They don't even need trimming.
# 它就自然會長成這樣子
They will become how they look like now.
# 好香啊
It smells so good.
# 你看 這是我山 我家山上的竹子哦
Look! These are the bamboos, on my, on my hill.
# 那麼多
So many
# 又大又肥
Big and thick
# 哇 這裡有野生靈芝哦
Wa! Here are some wild lingzhi.
# 一個
One
# 這裡還有個大點的
Here's a larger one too.
# 你看
Look!
# 這就是野靈芝
This is wild lingzhi.
# 下次 搞個兄弟家的雞煲湯
Next time, let's get a chicken from our buddy and make a stew.
# 不知道還有沒有
Is there any more?
# 今年雨水比較少
There's not so much rain this year.
# 沒多少野果
So there are not so many wild fruits.
# 現在都黃了
It has already turned yellow.
# 先把它扔下去吧
Let me throw them down first.
# 好啦 沒啦
Alright! No more!
# 就摘了這個麼兩個
We've just picked a couple of them here.
# 早知道不帶袋子來了
I wouldn't take the bag if I knew it.
# 試一下這個
Let me try this one,
# 看下好不好吃 今年的
and see if it tastes good. It's present year's
# 這果肉
The pulp...
# 好酸
Sour!
# 還沒酸
It's not yet ripe.
# 要這完年才熟它這個
They will only be ripe after the new year.
# 回去啦
Let's go back.
# 那麼兩個 (註︰不是真的兩個，而已數個，量不多)
Just a few